doorstep.
In two days going, they rode right up the long lake and passed out into the
river running. And now they could all see the lonely mountain towering grim
and tall before them. The stream was strong and they're going slow. At the
end of the third day, some miles up the river, they drew into the left or
western bank and disembarked. Here they were joined by the horses with other
provisions and necessaries and the ponies for their own use that had been
sent to meet them. They packed what they could on the ponies, and the rest was
made into a store under a tent. But none of the men of the town would stay with
them, even for the night so near the shadow of the mountain. Not at any rate
until the songs have come true, said they, it was easier to believe in the
dragon, and less easy to believe in Thoren in these wild parts. Indeed,
their stores had no need of any guard, for all the land was desolate and empty.
So their escort left them, making off swiftly down the river and the shorewood
paths, although the night was already drying on. They spent a cold and lonely
night, and their spirits fell. The next day they set out again. Balin and Bilbo
rode behind, each leading another pony heavily laden beside him. The others
were some way ahead, picking out a slow road, for there were no paths. They made
northwest, slanting away from the river running, and drawing ever nearer and
nearer to a great spur of the mountain that was flung out southwards towards
them. It was a weary journey, and a quiet and stealthy one. There was no
laughter or song or sound of harps, and the pride and hopes which had stirred in
their hearts at the singing of old songs by the lake died away to applauding
gloom. They knew that they were dry near to the end of their journey, and that it
might be a very horrible end. The land about them grew bleak and barren, though
once, as Thorin told them, it had been green and fair. There was little grass,
and before long there was neither bush nor tree, and only broken and blackened
stumps to speak of one's long vanished.
They were come to the desolation of the dragon, and they were come at the waning
of the year. They reached the skirts of the mountain all the same without
meeting any danger or any sign of the dragon other than the wilderness he had
made about his lair. The mountain lay dark and silent before them and ever
higher above them. They made their first camp on the western side of the great
southern spur which ended in a height called Ravenh Hill. On this there had
been an old watchpost, but they dared not climb it yet. It was too exposed.
Before setting out to search the western spurs of the mountain for the hidden
door on which all their hopes rested, Thoren sent out a scouting expedition to
spy out the land to the south were the front. Gates stood. For this purpose he
choose Balin and Feelely and Killy, and with them went Bilbo. They marched under
the gray and silent cliffs to the feet of Ravenhill. There the river, after
winding a wide loop over the valley of Dale, turned from the mountain on its
road to the lake, flowing swift and noisily. Its bank was bare and rocky,
tall and steep above the stream. And gazing out from it over the narrow
water, foaming and splashing among many boulders, they could see in the wide
valley shadowed by the mountains arms the gray ruins of ancient houses, towers, and walls.
There lies all that is left of Dale, said Balin. The mountain sides were
green with woods and all the sheltered valley, rich and pleasant in the days
when the bells rang in that town. He looked both sad and grim as he said
this. He had been one of Thoren's companions on the day the dragon came.
They did not dare to follow the river much further towards the gate. But they
went on beyond the end of the southern spur, unto lying hidden behind a rock.
They could look out and see the dark cavernous opening in a great cliff wall
between the arms of the mountain. Out of it the waters of the running river
sprang, and out of it too there came a steam and a dark smoke. Nothing moved in
the waste save the vapor in the water, and every now and again a black and
ominous crow. The only sound was the sound of the stony water and every now
and again the harsh croak of a bird.
Balon stuttered. "Let us return," he said. "We can do no good here, and I
don't like these dark birds. They look like spies of evil." "The front gate."
"The dragon is still alive and in the halls under the mountain then, or I
imagine so from the smoke," said the hobbit. That does not prove it, said
Balon, though I don't doubt you are right. But he might be gone away
sometime, or he might be lying out on the mountain side, keeping watch, and
still I expect smokes and steams would come out of the gates. All the holes
within must be filled with his foul reek. With such gloomy thoughts,
followed ever by croaking crows above them. They made their weary way back to
the camp. Only in June they had been guests in the fairhouse of Eland, and
though autumn was now crawling towards winter, that pleasant time now seemed years ago.
They were alone in the perilous waste without hope of further help. They were
at the end of their journey, but as far as ever, it seemed from the end of their
quest. None of them had much spirit left. Now strange to say Mr. Baggins had
more than the others. He would often borrow Thoren's map and gaze at it,
pondering over the runes and the message of the moon letters Elron had read. It
was he that made the dwarves begin the dangerous search on the western slopes
for the secret door. They moved their camp then to a long valley narrower than
the great dale in the south where the gates of the river stood and walled with
lower spurs of the mountain. Two of these here thrust forward west from the
main mass in long steep-sided ridges that fell ever downwards towards the
plane. On this western side, there were fewer signs of the dragon's marauding
feet, and there was some grass for their ponies. From this western camp, shadowed
all day by cliff and wall, until the sun began to sink towards the forest. Day by
day they toiled in party, searching for paths up the mountainside. If the map
was true, somewhere high above the cliff at the valley's head must stand the
secret door. Day by day they came back to their camp without success.
But at last, unexpectedly, they found what they were seeking. Fee and Keely
and the Hobbit went back one day down the valley and scrambled among the
tumbled rocks at its southern corner.
About midday, creeping behind a great stone that stood alone like a pillar,
Bilbo came on what looked like rough steps going upwards. Following these
excitedly, he and the dwarves found traces of a narrow track, often lost,
often rediscovered, that wandered onto the top of the southern ridge, and
brought them at last to a still narrower ledge, which turned north across the
face of the mountain.
Looking down, they saw that they were at the top of the cliff at the valley's
head, and were gazing down onto their own camp below. Silently, clinging to
the rocky wall on their right, they went in single file along the ledge, till the
wall opened, and they turned into a little steepwalled bay, grassy, floored,
still, and quiet. Its entrance, which they had found, could not be seen from
below because of the overhang of the cliff, nor from further off, because it
was so small that it looked like a dark crack and no more. It was not a cave,
and was open to the sky above. But at its inner end a flat wall rose up, that
in the lower part, close to the ground, was as smooth and upright as Mason's
work, but without a joint or crevice to be seen. No sign was there of post or
lentil or threshold, nor any sign of bar or bolt or keyhole. Yet they did not
doubt that they had found the door at last. They beat on it. They thrust and
pushed at it. They implored it to move.
They spoke fragments of broken spells of opening, and nothing stirred. At last,
tired out, they rested on the grass at its feet, and then at evening began
their long climb down. There was excitement in the camp that night. In
the morning they prepared to move once more. Only Bofur and Bomber were left
behind to guide the ponies and such stores as they had brought with them
from the river. The others went down the valley and up the newly found path and
so to the narrow ledge. Along this they could carry no bundles or packs so
narrow and breathless was it, with a fall of 150 ft beside them unto sharp
rocks below. But each of them took a good coil of rope wound tight about his
waist, and so at last, without mishap, they reached the little grassy bay.
There they made their third camp, hauling up what they needed from below
with their ropes. Down the same way, they were able occasionally to lower one
of the more active dwarves, such as Killy, to exchange such news as there
was, or to take a share in the guard below, while Bofer was hauled up to the
higher camp. Bomber would not come up either the rope or the path. "I am too
fat for such fly walks," he said. "I should turn dizzy and tread on my beard,
and then you would be 13 again, and the knotted ropes are too slender for my
weight." Luckily for him, that was not true, as you will see. In the meanwhile,
some of them explored the ledge beyond the opening and found a path that led
higher and higher onto the mountain, but they did not dare to venture very far
that way, nor was there much use in it.
Out up there a silence rained, broken by no bird or sound except that of the wind
in the crannies of stone. They spoke low and never called or sang, for danger
brooded in every rock. The others, who were busy with the secret of the door,
had no more success. They were too eager to trouble about the runes or the moon
letters, but tried without resting to discover where exactly in the smooth
face of the rock the door was hidden.
They had brought picks and tools of many sorts from Lake Town, and at first they
tried to use these, but when they struck the stone, the handle splintered and
jarred their arms cruy, and the steel heads broke or bent like lead. mining
work they saw clearly was no good against the magic that had shut this
door and they grew terrified too of the echoing noise. Bilbo found sitting on
the doorstep lonesome and weary some there was not a doorstep of course
really but they used to call the little grassy space between the wall and the
opening the doorstep in fun remembering Bilbo's words long ago at the unexpected
party in his hobbit hole when he said they could sit on the doorstep till they
thought of something and sit and think they did or wandered aimlessly about and
glumber and glumber they became. Their spirits had risen a little at the
discovery of the path, but now they sank into their boots, and yet they would not
give it up and go away.
The hobbit was no longer much brighter than the dwarves. He would do nothing
but sit with his back to the rock face and stare away west through the opening,
over the cliff, over the wide lands, to the black wall of Mirkwood, and to the
distances beyond, in which he sometimes thought he could catch glimpses of the
misty mountains, small and far. If the dwarves asked him what he was doing, he
answered. He said sitting on the doorstep and thinking would be my job,
not to mention getting inside. So I am sitting and thinking, but I am afraid he
was not thinking much of the job, but of what lay beyond the blue distance, the
quiet western land, and the hill and his hobbit hole under it. A large gray stone
lay in the center of the grass, and he stared moodily at it, or watched the
great snails. They seemed to love the little shut in bay with its walls of
cool rock, and there were many of them of huge size crawling slowly and sticky
along its sides. "Tomorrow begins the last week of autumn," said Thorin one
day. "And winter comes after autumn," said Bifur. "And next year after that,"
said Dwallan, "and our beards will grow till they hang down the cliff to the
valley before anything happens here."
What is our burglar doing for us? Since he has got an invisible ring and ought
to be a specially excellent performer now, I am beginning to think he might go
through the front gate and spy things out a bit. Bilbo heard this. The dwarves
were on the rocks just above the enclosure where he was sitting, and good
gracious, he thought. So that is what they are beginning to think, is it? It
is always poor me that has to get them out of their difficulties. at least
since the wizard left. Whatever am I going to do? I might have known that
something dreadful would happen to me in the end. I don't think I could bear to
see the unhappy valley of Dale again.
And as for that steaming gate that night he was very miserable and hardly slept.
Next day the dwarves all went wandering off in various directions. Some were
exercising the ponies down below. Some were roving about the mountainside. All
day Bilbo sat glooily in the grassy bay, gazing at the stone or out west through
the narrow opening. He had a queer feeling that he was waiting for
something. Perhaps the wizard will suddenly come back today, he thought. If
he lifted his head, he could see a glimpse of the distant forest. As the
sun turned west, there was a gleam of yellow upon its far roof, as if the
light caught the last pale leaves. Soon he saw the orange ball of the sun
sinking towards the level of his eyes.
He went to the opening and there pale and faint was a thin new moon above the
rim of earth. At that very moment he heard a sharp crack behind him. There on
the gray stone in the grass was an enormous thrush nearly cold black, its
pale yellow breast freckled with dark spots. Crack! It had caught a snail and
was knocking it on the stone. Crack!
crack. Suddenly, Bilbo understood.
Forgetting all danger, he stood on the ledge and hailed the dwarves, shouting
and waving. Those that were nearest came tumbling over the rocks and as fast as
they could along the ledge to him, wondering what on earth was the matter.
The others shouted to be hauled up the ropes, except Bomb, of course. He was
asleep. Quickly, Bilbo explained. They all fell silent, the hobbit standing by
the gray stone and the dwarves with wagging beards watching impatiently. The
sun sank lower and lower, and their hopes fell. It sank into a belt of
reened cloud and disappeared. The dwarves groaned, but still Bilbo stood
almost without moving. Evening was coming on. Evening was coming on. Then
suddenly, when their hope was lowest, a red ray of the sun escaped like a finger
through a rent in the cloud. A gleam of light came straight through the opening
into the bay and fell on the smooth rock face. The old thrush, who had been
watching from a high perch with beady eyes and headcocked on one side, gave a
sudden trill. There was a loud crack. A flake of rock split from the wall and
fell. A hole appeared suddenly about 3 ft from the ground. Quickly, trembling
less the chance should fade, the dwarves rushed to the rock and pushed in vain.
The key, the key, cried Bilbo. Where is Thorin? Thorin hurried up. The key,
shouted Bilbo. The key that went with the map. Try it now while there is still time.
Then Thoren stepped up and drew the key on its chain from round his neck. He put
it to the hole. It fitted and it turned.
Snap. The gleam went out. The sun sank.
The moon was gone. And evening sprang into the sky. Now they all pushed
together. And slowly a part of the rock wall gave way. Long straight cracks
appeared and widened. A door 5 ft high and three broad was outlined. And
slowly, without a sound, swung inwards.
It seemed as if darkness flowed out like a vapor from the hole in the
mountainside, and deep darkness in which nothing could be seen lay before their
eyes. A yawning mouth leading in and